Duncan Bennett

Email: bennettduncantai@gmail.com GitHub: https://github.com/dtb7793 Mobile: +1-707-318-5793

# RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interests are in applications of machine learning and data science to medicine and public health. Recently, I have worked on data augmentation using Variational Autoencoders to train deep models for spectral pathogen detection. I have also worked on computer vision and NLP tasks to analyze kidney transplant forms to inform medical infrastructure.

#### EDUCATION

#### University of Arizona

Tucson, AZ

PhD in Mathematics: (in progress)

Aug. 2019 - Present

### Western Washington University

Bellingham, WA

Master of Science in Mathematics; GPA: 3.94

Sept. 2016 - June. 2018

• MS Project: Classification of Finite Group Extensions and Group Cohomology

## University of Puget Sounds

Tacoma, WA

Bachelor of Science in Mathematics; GPA: 3.44

Aug. 2015 - May. 2015

o Senior Thesis: Algebraic Topology

#### RESEARCH AND WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Kidney Transplant Form OCR

Supervisor: Prof Marek Rychlik University of Arizona

June 2022- present

- o Implementation of computer vision algorithms such as PEARL to extract data from images of kidney transplant documents.
- o Develop foundation in the theory of Probablistic Graphical Models and Energy-based Models as it pertains to computer vision.
- Implementation of NLP algorithsm such as thid and grammar induction for document classification applied to medical documents.
- Written in MATLAB

#### Lightsense Technology Internship

Supervisor: Michael Stanley Lightsense Technology

June 2022-Dec 2022

- Develop machine learning models to classify and unmix high dimensional spectral data.
- Build and train variational autoencoders for data augmentation and outlier detection as part of a 2-class classification model.
- Research and present on modern papers in the intersection of machine learning and chemometrics.
- Collaborate with researchers in other fields of expertise.
- o Maintain python, keras and tensorflow code on github.

#### Response-guided Principal Component Classification

Supervisor: Prof Helen Zhang University of Arizona

Aug. 2020-present

- The adaptation of response-guided principal component regression to logistic regression for binary classification.
- Improvements to convergence, robustness compared to logistic regression by reformlating in terms of principal components. Improvement by factor of 10 to 100 in Kullback-Leibner divergence with respect to density estimation.
- o Continued research to generalize this method to generalized linear models to combined response-guided PCA with Poisson regression etc.
- Written in R with glmnet, ggplot2 and original library

### Scoliosis Medical Imaging

Supervisor: Prof Marek Rychlik University of Arizona

July 2021-Dec. 2021

• Build and train CNN with up/down sampling to preform semantic segmentation of spine X-rays.

- From semantic segmentaion, train output layer for quadrilateral estimation of vertebra and calculation of Cobb angle using techniques from density estimation.
- Preliminary results show improvements in quadrilateral segmentation accuracy compared to tradiation regression approaches.
- Written in MATLAB with image processing and fuzzy logic toolkits.

# Supervised Principal Component Regression

Supervisor: Prof Ning Hao University of Arizona

July 2021-Aug. 2021

- Developed dimension reduction methods that principal components based on the covariance of the predictors and variance of the response data.
- Written in R with glmnet, ggplot2 and original library.

## The Order Complex of Cyclic Groups and its Homotopy Type

Supervisor: Prof James Bernhard University of Puget Sound

May 2011-Oct. 2011

 $\circ$  The subgroup lattice functor distributes over direct products and thus for abelian groups, the question of homotopy type can be reduced down to that of the maximal p-subgroups. This results in the subgroup lattice is homotopy equivalent to a wedge of spheres of varying dimension.

### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- MATLAB: Familiarity with MATLAB for machine learning and toolboxes such as Statistics and Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Image Processing, Signal Processing, DSP System and Fuzzy Logic.
- R: Familiarity with R for statistical analysis and libraries such as dplyr, ggplot2, knitr, and glmnet.
- Python: Jupyter Notebooks, Keras, scikit-learn, pyplot, ...
- Computer Skills:
  - o Git/Github
  - o Linux (Ubuntu, Fedora)
  - o Emacs
  - o bash and terminal navigation
- Relevant Coursework: Statistical Machine Learning, Numerical Analysis and Algorithms, Experiment Design, Advanced Regression Analysis, Probability, Statistics, Natural Language Processing, Stochastic Processes, Probabilistics Graphical Models.

#### Presentations and Talks

R Tutorial: Basics for NLP  University of Arizona: DataFest 2023	Tucson, AZ Mar 2023
• Variational Autoencoders University of Arizona: Multilingual OCR Seminar	Tucson, AZ Sept 2022
• Variational Autoencoders and Data Augmentation  Lightsense Technology	Tucson, AZ  July 2022
• Speech and Language Processing (Series) University of Arizona: Multilingual OCR Seminar	Tucson, AZ Spring 2022
• Response-guided Principal Component Classification University of Arizona: RTG Mini Conference	Tucson, AZ Dec 2020
• The Order Complex of Cyclic Groups and its Homotopy Type Western Washington University: Western's Association of Mathematics (W $\alpha$ M)	Bellingham, WA  May 2018
• The Cohomology of Finite Groups and Group Extensions Western Washington University: Mathematics Department Colloquium	Bellingham, WA  May 2018
• The Order Complex of Cyclic Groups and its Homotopy Type University of Puget Sound: Math/CS Seminar	Tacoma, WA April 2016

### AWARDS

AWARDS	
Galileo Circle Award  (University of Arizona)	August 2022
Outstanding Masters Graduate Award	, and the second
(Western Washington University) Academic Merit	May 2018
Elias Bond Graduate Fellowship	
(Western Washington University) Academic Merit	May 2017
Richard Greene Graduate Scholarship	
(Western Washington University) Academic Merit	May 2017
TEACHING	
University of Arizona	Tucson, AZ
Graduate Teaching Assistant	Aug. 2019 – Present
o Math 112 Algebra	
o Math 120R Pre-Calculus	
Whatcom Community College	Bellingham, WA
• Adjunct Instructor	Sept. 2018 – June. 2019
o Math 97 Elementary Algebra I	
o Math 98 Elementary Albegra II	
o Math 141 Pre-Calculus I	
o Math 151 Calculus I	
Western Washington University	Bellingham, WA
• Graduate Teaching Assistant	Sept. 2016 – June. 2018
o Math 112 Algebra	
o Math 114 Pre-Calculus I	
o Math 115 Pre-Calculus II	
Extra Curricular	
Pi Mu Epsilon (Math Honors Society)	Tacoma, WA
Founding Member of University of Puget Sound chapter	2015
Arizona ASA DataFest Mentor	Online/AZ
Graduate Student Mentor	$2021 ext{-}present$

- $\circ~$  Mentored undergraduate competitors through fast-paced data competition using large datasets from industry.
- $\circ~$  Occurs over 3 days every spring.
- o Given tutorials on relevant skills in a short timeframe.